Preliminary Guide to the Howard W. Hallman papers, 1945-2003 MS2283
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Howard W. Hallman papers
1945-2003
1961-1983
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Hallman, Howard W
MS2283
38.5 Linear Feet
This collection is the working papers of Howard W. Hallman. Howard Hallman worked for many years within the citizen participation movement in American cities from the middle 1960s through the 1980s. The collection containes correspondence, newsletters, publications, and reports from 1945-2003 with the bulk falling within 1961-1983. Topics of these materials include city bugeting, citizen participation, decentralization of government services and poverty.
Other Finding Aids
There is NUSA archival material can be found at www.nusa.org.
Biography
Howard W. Hallman spent thirteen years engaged in housing and community improvement programs in Philadelphia, PA and New Haven, CT. From 1969 to 1983 he headed the Civic Action Institute, which conducted research, training, and technical assistance on employment training programs, local government decentralization, citizen participation, and neighborhood self-help activities.
In 1976 Hallman was the principal founder of Neighborhoods, USA, a national association of neighborhood leaders and local officials. He has conducted studies and made presentations in Sweden, Canada, Puerto Rico, Yugoslavia, Israel, Japan, and Turkey. He is author of more than 250 publications including nine books, such as Small and Large Together: Governing the Metropolis and Neighborhoods: Their Place in Urban Life.
Hallman has also been a peace activist since his college days at the University of Kansas. His peace activism has lead him to work towards nuclear disarmament. He is also chair of Methodists United for Peace with Justice, a national association of laity and clergy and is active in local church activities.
Scope and Contents note
This collection contains government publications, organizational publications, newsletters, research materials, reports, and newspaper articles. These materials date from 1945-2003 with the bulk falling within 1961-1985. The subject matter within this collection cover citizen participation in neighborhood decentralization, revitalization, and community organizing. The records deal with background material on emergence of community corporations in the 1960s, studies and reports on creation of little city halls, neighborhood councils, and other modes of municipal decentralization in various cities (1969-77), training and technical assistance on citizen participation in community development and neighborhood self-help activities (1977-83), articles and papers on these topics by such persons as Jim Cunningham, Joseph Zimmerman, Milton Kotler, and Donna Shalala (1960s, 1970s), citizen participation in local budget making including reports covering 15 years in New York City, Dayton, St. Paul, and Portland, Oregon, studies for city charter commissions in Pittsburgh (1975) and New York (1989), reports and newsletters from national organizations dealing with neighborhoods, reports developed by the National Commission on Neighborhoods (1977-79), papers on neighborhood topics prepared for HUD by various authors (1983), and community crime prevention (1980s).
Arrangement
Arranged in the original order donated with original folder titles.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Howard W. Hallman, 2010 (2010.011)
Unemployment; Neighborhood planning -- United States -- Citizen participation.; Neighborhood planning; Budget -- Citizen participation.; Poverty; Decentralization in government United States; Local government -- Citizen participation.; Housing; Center for Governmental Studies (Washington, D.C.); Community Action Program (U.S.); Hallman, Howard W; Civic Action Institute (Washington, D.C.)
- Neighborhood Governance material for HUD paper, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  General
  This material was originally housed in a three-ring binder.
- HUD papers [1/3], 1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- HUD papers [2/3], 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- HUD papers [3/3], 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Neighborhood book xerox extracts from articles unsorted, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- CDBG Citizen Participation studies [1/2], undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- CDBG Citizen Participation studies [2/2], undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Neighborhoods Their Place in American Life notes for first half, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Neighborhoods Their Place in American Life notes for second half [1/2], undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Neighborhoods Their Place in American Life notes for second half [2/2], undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Neighbhorhoods Their Place in American Life material on social community, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Neighborhood Decentralization Bulletins local descriptions [1/2], 1973-1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Neighborhood Decentralization Bulletins local descriptions [2/2], 1973-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Look Back on the Future: Poverty and Neighborhood Action conference papers [1/3], 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  As a consultant to the National Neighborhood Coalition, Howard Hallman developed the substance of this conference. This material was originally housed in a three-ring binder.
- Look Back on the Future: Poverty and Neighborhood Action conference papers [2/3], 1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Look Back on the Future: Poverty and Neighborhood Action conference papers [3/3], 1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Citizen roles in city budget making, 04/1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  The documents in this folder were not originally in a folder. The folder title was supplied by staff.
- Budget process, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Budget process, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Budget Study for National Civic League, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Citizens rols in city budget making 1st draft, 03/1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Dayton -- Budget Process, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Dayton -- Budget process, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- CDBG and Priority Board, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Budget citizen involvement, Dayton Ohio, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- St. Paul -- Budget Process, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- St. Paul -- Citizen involvement, 1982-1989 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- St. Paul -- Citizen involvement, 1983-1988 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Portland -- Budget Process, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Conserve Neighborhoods newsletter, 1982-1984 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Local initiatives newsletter, 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Neighborhood Notes newsletter, 1979-1980 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- The Neighborhood Works newsletter, 03/31/1978-05/23/1980 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- The Neighborhood Works newsletter, 06/13/1980-10/31/1981 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- The Neighborhood Works newsletter, 11/16/1981-05/1983 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- The Neighborhood Works newsletter, 06/1983-08/1984 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Hallman's Publications: Bureau of Government Research KU, 1949-1952 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Montgomery County, MD, 1952-1956 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Howard Hallman's writings for Philadelphia Housing Association [1/2], 1952-1958 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Howard Hallman's writings for Philadelphia Housing Association [2/2], 1952-1958 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Howard Hallman's writings on metropolitan issues, 1953-1958 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Howard Hallman's writings on housing and urban renewal, 1956-1962 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Howard Hallman's writings on The Middle Ground Program New Haven, CT, 1959-1962 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Howard Hallman's writings on Community Progress, Inc. New Haven, CT, 1959-1962 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Howard Hallman's writings Social Reform in Urban Communities, New Haven, CT, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Howard Hallman's writings Planning with the Poor, New Haven, CT, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Howard Hallman's writings Senate Committee for the study of the Poverty Program, Washington, DC, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Howard Hallman's writings The Community Action Program an interperative analysis, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Howard Hallman's writings Community Action Program, 1964-1968 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Howard Hallman's writings Historical highlights of the Poverty Program, Washington, DC, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Howard Hallman's writings Poverty, Employment, Social Reform, Washington, DC, 1968-1969 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Howard Hallman's writings The Future of the Poverty Program, Washington, DC, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  written on original file: prepared for conference on poverty program (the urban coalition)
- Howard Hallman's writings Community Control Study, Washington DC, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Howard Hallman's writings C.G.S. Municipal Decentralization Citizen participation in program implementation (IULA conf.) Zagrev, Yugoslavia, 10/13/1971 (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Howard Hallman's writings C.G.S. Municipal Decentratlization, 1969-1975 (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Howard Hallman's writings C.G.S. Municipal Decentratlization Community corporations and neighborhood control, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Howard Hallman's writings C.G.S. Municipal Decentratlization Neighborhood ideas, 1977-1983 (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Howard Hallman's writings Federally financed citizen participation, 1970 April (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Howard Hallman's writings The Neighborhood as an Organizational Unit: An Historical Perspective, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Howard Hallman's writings admin. decentralization and community control, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Howard Hallman's writings Neighborhood Management (for ICMA) public management series, 1971 January (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Howard Hallman's writings CP in urban community development, 1971 November (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Howard Hallman's writings Advising the President a panel, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Howard Hallman's writings Essays and conference reports (columbia) urban community development strategies, 1972 February (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Howard Hallman's writings Government by Neighborhoods pamphlet, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Howard Hallman's writings ASPO conference - chicago, 1974 May 11 - 1974 May 16 (Box 13, Folder 9)
- Howard Hallman's writings Metropolitan Federalism and neighborhood Government (ACIR conf.), 1975 February 21 (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Howard Hallman's writings C.G.S. Employment and Training Development of the concept of a local system for the delivery of manpower services, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 11)
- Howard Hallman's writings C.G.S. Employment and Training A Graduated Family Allowance, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 12)
- Howard Hallman's writings C.G.S. Employment and Training local manpower system, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 13)
- Howard Hallman's writings C.G.S. Employment and Training National manpower planning ASPA Conference NY, NY, 1972 March 24 (Box 13, Folder 14)
- Howard Hallman's writings C.G.S. Employment and Training Achieving full employment and role of manpower programs, 1972 (Box 13, Folder 15)
- Howard Hallman's writings C.G.S. Employment and Training Unmasking the unemployed the personnel administrator, 1972 August (Box 13, Folder 16)
- Howard Hallman's writings C.G.S. Employment and Training Jobs for All, 1972 (Box 13, Folder 17)
- Howard Hallman's writings Statement before the Select Subcommittee on Labor, 1973 March 22 (Box 13, Folder 18)
- Howard Hallman's writings Statement before the Select Subcommittee on Employment, Manpower and Poverty, 1973 May 03 (Box 13, Folder 19)
- Howard Hallman's writings Statement before the Select Subcommittee on Employment, Poverty and Migratory labor, 1975 June 04 (Box 13, Folder 20)
- Howard Hallman's writings Ideas on economic planning, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 21)
- Howard Hallman's writings Equality, Opportunity, and Community, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 22)
- Howard Hallman's writings citizen involvement in the local budget process, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 23)
- Howard Hallman's writings citizen priorities and the local budget process, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 24)
- Howard Hallman's writings, 1980-2000 (Box 13, Folder 25)
- Center for Governmental Studies, 1969-1974 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  Biographical / Historical
  In 1978 the Center for Government Studies changed its name to the Civic Action Institute.
- Center for Government Studies: Minutes of Board of Directors meetings [1/3], 1969 October 10 - 1970 May 7 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Center for Government Studies: Minutes of Board of Directors meetings [2/3], 1970 October 23 - 1972 September 29 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Center for Government Studies: Minutes of Board of Directors meetings [3/3], 1973 January 26 - 1974 November 15 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Civic Action Institute Minutes of Board meetings, 1978 November - 1980 December (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Articles and publications on local budget process, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Article on local budget process [previously labeled misc.], undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Local budget process Resource Allocation, undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Local budget process General Revenue Sharing and Citizen Participation, undated (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Local budget process Atlanta, undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Local budget process Cincinnati, undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Local budget process Dayton, undated (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Local budget process Juneau, undated (Box 15, Folder 8)
- Local budget process New York [1/3], undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
- Local budget process New York [2/3], undated (Box 15, Folder 10)
- Local budget process New York [3/3], undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Local budget process Philadelphia, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Local budget process Portland, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Local budget process St. Paul, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Cities, Neighborhoods, CP A Bibliography of Decentralization, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Cities, Neighborhoods, CP Atlanta, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Cities, Neighborhoods, CP Birmingham, Alabama, undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Cities, Neighborhoods, CP Chicago, undated (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Cities, Neighborhoods, CP Chicago Rehab Network, undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Cities, Neighborhoods, CP Des Moines, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Cities, Neighborhoods, CP Eugene, undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Cities, Neighborhoods, CP [Eastown Aquinas College], undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Cities, Neighborhoods, CP Indianapolis, Indiana, undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Cities, Neighborhoods, CP Indianapolis, Indiana Neighborhood Decentralization, undated (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Cities, Neighborhoods, CP Indiana (Charter), undated (Box 17, Folder 7)
- Cities, Neighborhoods, CP Newark, undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
- Cities, Neighborhoods, CP Citzens League Minneapolis - St. Paul, Minnesota [1/2], undated (Box 17, Folder 9)
- Cities, Neighborhoods, CP Citzens League Minneapolis - St. Paul, Minnesota [2/2], undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
- cities: Neighborhoods, CP New York, undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
- cities: Neighborhoods, CP Citizens Committee for New York City, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
- cities: Neighborhoods, CP New York Decentralization [1/2], Circa 1960s-1790s (Box 18, Folder 4)
- cities: Neighborhoods, CP New York Decentralization [2/2], Circa 1960s-1790s (Box 18, Folder 5)
- cities: Neighborhoods, CP New York Charter City [1/2], Circa 1970s (Box 18, Folder 6)
- Cities: Neighborhoods, CP New York Charter City [2/2], Circa 1970's (Box 19, Folder 1)
- Cities: Neighborhoods, CP New York: Schools, undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
- Cities: Neighborhoods, CP City Limits, 1979 June/July - 1982 January (Box 19, Folder 3)
- Cities: Neighborhoods, CP Neighborhood, undated (Box 19, Folder 4)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, Alliance for Neighborhood Government, Circa 1970's (Box 19, Folder 5)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, American Jewish Committee, Circa 1970's (Box 19, Folder 6)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, Barter, Circa 1970's (Box 20, Folder 1)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, Bartering, Circa 1970's (Box 20, Folder 2)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, California Neighborhoods, Circa 1970's (Box 20, Folder 3)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, Center for Community Change, Circa 1970's (Box 20, Folder 4)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, Institute for Neighborhood Studies, Circa 1970's (Box 20, Folder 5)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, Institute for Responsive Education, Circa 1970's (Box 20, Folder 6)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, Institute for Responsive Education, Circa 1970's (Box 20, Folder 7)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, National Association of Neighborhoods [1/3], Circa 1980's (Box 20, Folder 8)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, National Association of Neighborhoods [2/3], 1978-1981 (Box 21, Folder 1)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, National Association of Neighborhoods [3/3], 1978-1980 (Box 21, Folder 2)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, League of Women Voters, Circa 1970s (Box 21, Folder 3)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, National Association of Neighborhoods 10th National Conference Milwaukee, Circa 1980s (Box 21, Folder 4)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, National Association of Neighborhoods Bulletin, 1980 (Box 21, Folder 5)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, Ellie Wegener Civic Action Institute Washington DC, undated (Box 21, Folder 6)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, National Commission on Neighborhoods, Circa 1980s (Box 21, Folder 7)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, National Committee for Citizens in Education, Circa 1980s (Box 21, Folder 8)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, National Conference of Neighborhood Women, Circa 1980s (Box 21, Folder 9)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, National Neighbors, Inc., Circa 1980s (Box 21, Folder 10)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, Declaration of Neighborhood Rules, Rights, and Responsibilities, undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, Neighborhood Postage Stamp, 1986 (Box 22, Folder 2)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, History of War on Poverty, Circa 1980's (Box 22, Folder 3)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, Neighborhood Organization Research Group [1/2], 1980-1981 (Box 22, Folder 4)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, Neighborhood Organization Research Group [2/2], 1980-1981 (Box 22, Folder 4)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, Neighborhood Organization Research Group [2/2], 1979-1980 (Box 22, Folder 5)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, OEO National Advisory Council, 1968-1972 (Box 22, Folder 6)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, (SNAP) [Stimulating the Neighborhood Action Process], 1979-1980 (Box 22, Folder 7)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, (SNAP) [Stimulating the Neighborhood Action Process], Circa 1980's (Box 22, Folder 8)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, (SNAP) [Stimulating the Neighborhood Action Process] Suport System Clearinghouse, Circa 1980 (Box 23, Folder 1)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, United Neighborhood Centers of America, Circa 1980 (Box 23, Folder 2)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, Workshop in Political Theory [1/2], Circa 1978 (Box 23, Folder 3)
- Organizations re Neighborhoods, Workshop in Political Theory [2/2], Circa 1978 (Box 23, Folder 4)
- Organized Against Crime, The National Center for Citizen Involvement [1/2], 1980 (Box 23, Folder 5)
- Organized Against Crime, The National Center for Citizen Involvement [2/2], 1980 (Box 23, Folder 6)
- Community Safety Information Project Center for Urban Education, 1981 September (Box 23, Folder 7)
- Neighborhood-based Arson Control, A guide to citizen-initiated legal remedies, 1983 September (Box 23, Folder 8)
- Crime Prevention publications, 1974-1984 (Box 24, Folder 1)
- Crime Prevention publications, 1973,1984 (Box 24, Folder 2)
- Neighborhood Justice Centers publicaitons, 1979-1980 (Box 24, Folder 3)
- Evaluation of Operation Neighborhood An Urban Institute paper, 1973 December (Box 24, Folder 4)
- The Pilot Police Project by Rita Mae Kelly, 1972 January (Box 24, Folder 5)
- On Improving Police-Community Relations by Rita Mae Kelly, 1972 January (Box 24, Folder 6)
- Employment laws, regs local chief executives' perception of policy-making and management needs vol. 1, 1975 February (Box 25, Folder 1)
- Employment laws, regs local chief executives' perception of policy-making and management needs vol. II, 1975 February (Box 25, Folder 2)
- Employment laws, regs Human Resources Planning, 1965 (Box 25, Folder 3)
- Employment laws, regs Publications, 1969-1983 (Box 25, Folder 4)
- Neighborhood Economic Enterprises--N. Kotler, 1978 (Box 25, Folder 5)
- Publication: Analysis of the commitment of citizens of Pittsburgh's neighborhoods and policy recommendations for city government, September 1978 (Box 25, Folder 6)
- Publication: Between community and city bureaucracy New York's district manager experiment, 1973 February (Box 25, Folder 7)
- Publication: Changing public attitudes on governmnet and taxes, 1982 (Box 26, Folder 1)
- Publication: Citizen participation: a review and commentary on federal policies and practices, 1970 January (Box 26, Folder 2)
- Publication: Cleveland's urban renewal experience, 1973 December (Box 44, Folder 4)
- Publication: Comprehensive neighborhood programs findings and conclusions of a neighborhood center study, 1970 October 15 (Box 26, Folder 3)
- Publication: The cost of sprawl, 1974 April (Box 39, Folder 5)
- Publication: Decentralizing city government an evaluation of the New York City district manager experiment [1/2], 1975 September (Box 26, Folder 4)
- Publication: Decentralizing city government an evaluation of the New York City district manager experiment [2/2], 1975 September (Box 26, Folder 5)
- Publication: A discussion draft for a symposium on decentralizing New York City government, 1970 (Box 39, Folder 1)
- Publication: District service cabinents and the office of neighborhood government, 1973 November (Box 26, Folder 6)
- Publication: Effects of neighborhood consensus on services delivery Human Services bibliography series, 1981 July (Box 26, Folder 7)
- Publication: Life with Boston: a citizen's asssessment of services, 1972 June (Box 38, Folder 1)
- Publication: Manual for neighborhood development corporation demonstration program, undated (Box 44, Folder 8)
- Publication: Metropolitan Governance Maze in the United States by Joseph Zimmerman, 1978 August 21 (Box 44, Folder 6)
- Publication: MML citizen participation manual, 1977 November (Box 26, Folder 8)
- Publication: Municipal service districts a background study for decentralization of Detroit, 1973 September (Box 44, Folder 7)
- Publication: Neighborhood action vol. 1 and 3, 1970 (Box 49, Folder 10)
  Scope and Contents
  In volume 1 Howard Hallman wrote notes on the inside front cover.
- Publication: The Neighborhood Center Community Action, 1966 July (Box 39, Folder 2)
- Publication: Neighborhood development organizations: why their projects succeed or fail and how they grow in the process, 1982 August (Box 26, Folder 9)
- Publication: Neighborhood organizations and community development, 1983 January (Box 27, Folder 1)
- Publication: Neighborhood watch Neighborhoods against crime a community anti-crime program, 1981 (Box 38, Folder 5)
- Publication: The neighborhoods, the city, and the region working papers on jurisdiction and structure, 1973 January (Box 27, Folder 2)
- Publication: The new grass roots government decentralization and citizen participation in urban areas, 1972 January (Box 27, Folder 3)
- Publication: New York City neighborhood project administrative decentralization and the public, 1974 December (Box 38, Folder 3)
- Publication: New York City neighborhood project the future of community control, 1974 September (Box 27, Folder 4)
- Publication: New York self help handbook, 1977 (Box 27, Folder 5)
- Publication: The office of neighborhood government and community leaders in Washington Heights -- Inwood, 1973 October (Box 27, Folder 6)
- Publication: Partners part 1: Neighborhood revitalization through partnership and Part 2: Whittier Neighborhood Minneapolis case study, 1981 (Box 39, Folder 3)
- Publication: Partnership for neighborhood preservation: a citizens' handbook, 1978 December (Box 27, Folder 7)